Guide to the Irving Weissman Photograph Collection ALBA.PHOTO.165
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irving Weissman Photographs
1937-1991
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Weissman, Irving, 1913-1998
ALBA.PHOTO.165
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Irving Weissman (1913-1998) was a labor activist and a member of the Young Communist League before he went to fight in the Spanish Civil War. In Spain he trained and fought with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion. Many of the images in this collection were acquired by Weissman in the course of his service with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion in Spain. The collection contains combat and non-combat photographs, portraits, images of Czechoslovakian volunteers interned at the Gurs Concentration Camp in France, the U.S. veterans' fiftieth anniversary trip to Spain and a veterans memorial meeting.
289 black and white photographs sized from 1 ¾ x 2 ¼ inches to 8 ½ x 11 inches and 10 negatives sized from 2 ½ x 3 ¼ to 5 ½ x 4 inches.
Provenance
The Irving Weissman Photograph Collection was donated by Mr. Weissman to the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives, then held at Brandeis University, in 1994. This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The images in the Weissman Photograph Collection were separated from the Weissman manuscript material at the time of processing.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Irving Weissman (1913-1998) grew up in a Polish-Jewish immigrant family in New York City. For further biographical information on Irving Weissman, and to review the scope and contents of his manuscript collection see Guide to the Irving Weissman Papers, ALBA #165.
Weissman departed for Spain on the SS American Importer on May 8, 1937. In Spain, he trained with the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion and went into action with that battalion on the Aragon front and at Fuentes de Ebro in September and October 1937. Weissman fell ill at the end of October and was sent with a delegation of the 15th International Brigade to Barcelona, where he performed guard duties while he recovered. He rejoined the MacKenzie-Papineau Battalion in December 1937. Weissman left Spain on December 15, 1938.
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Photographs. The Irving Weissman Collection contains 289 prints (including seven contact sheets) containing images of Steve Nelson, George Brodsky, Norman Berkowitz, Stanley Postek, George Watt, Abraham Osheroff, Albert Prago, Al Koslow, Moe Fishman, John Koblich, Abe Smorodin, Hy Wallach, Kenneth Graeber, Adolf Ross, George Cullinen, Stephen Zak, Pete Smith, John Tisa, Louis Gordon, Art Shields, John Robinson; Czechoslovakian volunteers at the Gurs Concentration Camp in France, U.S. veterans' Fiftieth Anniversary Trip to Spain and a veterans memorial meeting.
Series II: Negatives. Ten negatives containing images of Peter Frye, Hy Stone, Czechoslovakian volunteers at the Gurs Concentration Camp in France, VALB Fiftieth Anniversary Trip, Florida Veterans, Irish Veterans, a painting of Anthony and Edna Toney, and an unidentified couple. Eight of the ten negatives match prints in the collection.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically by topic. The photographic prints are identified by four numbers separated by colons. The first number refers to the collection number, the second to the box number, the third to the folder number, and the fourth to the individual print. For example, the first print in this collection is labeled 165:1:1:1. The negatives are numbered in a similar fashion. Prints with matching negatives bear the notation "Have Negative," negatives that match prints have the number of the matching print written on the negative sleeve.
The files are grouped into two series:
Missing Title
I, Photographs
II, Negatives
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Irving Weissman Papers, ALBA #165
Barcelona (Spain); Negatives (photographic); Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Pictorial works; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Black-and-white photographs.; Fishman, Mosess (Moe), 1916-2007; Prago, Albert; Smorodin, Abe; Tisa, John; Wallach, Hy; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Brigada Internacional, XV; Weissman, Irving, 1913-1998; Nelson, Steve, 1903-1993; Koslow, Alan; Postek, Stanley, 1912-1991; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Osheroff, Abe; Berkowitz, Norman; Brodsky, George
- Series I. Photographs
  - Contact Sheets: 7 sheets, all showing a Veterans Memorial Gathering. (Among the veterans pictured are: Steve Nelson, George Brodsky, Norman Berkowitz, Stanley Postek, George Watt, Abraham Osheroff, Albert Prago, Al Koslow, Moe Fishman, John Koblich, Abe Smorodin, Hy Wallach, Adolf (Buster) Ross, George A. Cullinen Jr., Stephen Zak, Pete Smith, Court Bevensee, John Tisa, Louis Gordon, John Tisa, John Robinson, John Toutoloff, James Yates, Oscar Hunter, Irving Weissman, Nat Gross, and Ken Graeber.), {1970s or 1980s] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Czechoslovakian Volunteers: Gurs Concentration Camp, France, ca.1937-1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Damaged/Shelled Buildings: Belchite, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary Veterans Trip: Orrin Feldt (far left), Joe Hautaneimi (second from right), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Florida Veterans: (Back Row) Mike Jimenez, Norman Berkowitz, Bill Rappaport, Irving Gold, Milt Felson, Marvin Penn (Canadian), Tom Keenan, John Tisa; (Front Row) Hy Hirsch, Rubin Erlich, Rose Wachsman (Sorkin), Joe Aznar, Lake Worth Florida, Mar 24, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Frye, Peter: Portrait, post-SCW, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Goldring, Ben: Portrait, post-SCW, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Labor History News: Memorial to Irish Veterans, Spain, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Labor History News: Veterans on Cover, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Memorial to Jewish Volunteers Killed in Spain, Barcelona, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Noble, Marion: with Robert Steck, post-SCW, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Shuman, Jack: with anti-Fascist Posters, post-SCW, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Spanish Civilians: Celia, Murcia, May 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Stone, Hy: Behind the Lines, Rest and Relaxation, Jarama, Jun 1937 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Toney, Anthony: Painting of Anthony and Edna Toney, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Veterans: Art Taylor, Marion Noble, Phil Raymond, Robert Steck, Seattle, WA, Oct 1967 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - VALB: Anti-Apartheid March, Jun 14, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: Charles Clements (l) Steve Nelson (r), undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: Charles Clements, Steve Nelson, Harry Fisher, Henry Foner, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: Frances Patai, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: Marty Balter (l) Steve Nelson (r), undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: Moe Fishman (standing), Steve Nelson (being hugged), Charles Clements (hugging Nelson), undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: Moe Fishman and Unidentified Men, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: (l to r) Ruth Epstein, Jacob Epstein, Jack Bjoze, Clarence Kailin, Dave Engleson, Jess Wallach, Blas Padrino (rear), Len Levenson, Ruby Schneiderman, Charles Nusser, Bill Sennett, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Veterans Memorial Meeting: Steve Nelson, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Veterans Monument: Sierra de Pandols, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Weissman, Irving: Portrait, post-SCW, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Weissman, Irving: Portrait, Spain, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Winston, Henry: with Oscar Hunter, Yusif Story, Randall (Pete) Smith, Len Levenson, U.S., May 12, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Negative: Czechoslovakian Volunteers, Gurs Concentration Camp, France, ca.1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Series II. Negatives
  - Negative: Fiftieth Anniversary Veterans Trip, Orrin Feldt (far left), Joe Hautaneimi (second from right), 1987 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Negative: Florida Veterans, Mar 24, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Negative: Hy Stone, Behind the Lines, Rest and Relaxation, Jarama, Jun 1937 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Negative: Labor History News, Memorial to Irish Veterans, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Negative: Labor History News, Veterans on Cover, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Negative: Peter Frye, Portrait, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Negative: Painting of Anthony and Edna Toney, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Negative: Unidentified Couple, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)